A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, South and Southeast Asia, Karachi and Islamabad, Pakistan, Field Office Files FA647
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, South and Southeast Asia, Karachi and Islamabad, Pakistan, Field Office Files
1951-1981
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA647
21.28 Cubic Feet
19 boxes -- 2 document boxes, 17 cubic foot boxes
Conditions Governing Access note
Material is open for scholarly research, with prior archival review.
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research.
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series by file type.
Scope and Contents
Contains travel and study awards and subject files.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Biographical / Historical
Segment One: International Activities of the Ford Foundation: An Overview
The Foundation's aspiration to become a national and international philanthropy for the advancement of human welfare was first formally expressed in the seminal 1949 report of the Gaither Study Committee, >Report of the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program (RAC Library, call letters 361.7 GAI ), which was commissioned by the Board of Trustees to chart the Foundation’s future. Foundation Trustees launched Ford’s international grantmaking activities in 1950 when they approved the committee’s report and its embrace of peace, democracy, and freedom. Since then, the Foundation has tackled these goals using a variety of strategies and responding to changing contexts, from the Cold War to the 1989 fall of the Berlin Wall and beyond.
Toward the Foundation’s aspiration‎al goal, "the establishment of peace", its international activities have comprised a wide range of conceptual approaches and focus areas. These include international affairs, international studies, international understanding, arms control and disarmament, international law, international economic concerns, and overseas development in nearly every region of the world. Three distinct periods emerge for the international grantmaking defined by external contextual changes and internal changes in Foundation leadership and structures: the expansion era of 1950-1965; the transition and restructuring years of 1966-1988; and the post-1989 shift away from Cold War dichotomies. During each of the distinct historical periods the consistent objectives were: 1) to ensure freedom and democracy in developed countries; 2) to foster education and international understanding in all countries; and 3) to contribute to the social, economic, and political development of less developed countries.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 2. Period Sketch - The Expansion Era 1950-1965
The Ford Foundation’s expansion era (1950-1965) began when the Gaither Study Committee Report placed “peace” as the area of top priority for the Foundation and set the Ford Foundation on a global course. Board Chair Henry Ford II writing in the 1951 Annual Report of the Foundation, identified “the danger of war” as the “the prime threat to human welfare today.” Under the leadership of the three Ford Foundation presidents in this period-- Paul Hoffman, H. Rowan Gaither and Henry Heald--and several key trustees, notably the two seriatim chairs, John J. McCloy and Julius A. Stratton, the Foundation programs were largely informed by the post-World War II desire to avoid nuclear war and promote greater understanding among the world’s peoples, strengthening of the United Nations, and enhancing both private and public American participation in world affairs. The strong board presence of university presidents and former leaders of postwar reconstruction efforts in Europe also helped to inform Ford’s approach to building the field of peace and international security in the United States and encouraged extensive overseas activities.
For example, the first three presidents of the expanded Foundation ranged from government and business leadership experience to academic and nonprofit: Paul Hoffman (at Ford, 1950-1953) ran the Marshall Plan in Europe; H. Rowan Gaither Staffer (1948-1953), President (1953-1956) and Trustee (1956-1958) had MIT and Rand experience; Henry Heald, former president, Illinois Institute of Technology and New York University, President (1956-1966). The trustees also ran the leadership gamut from government and nonprofits to academic: Trustee John J. McCloy (from 1953; chair, 1959-1965) was assistant Secretary of War during World War II and chairman of the Council on Foreign Relations; and Trustee Julius A. Stratton (Trustee from 1955; chair, 1966-1970) was president of MIT.
When Ford became an international foundation in 1950, it had a small staff and operated through separate funds. The expansive period in the 1950s and 1960s resulted in a large number of field offices, which increased Ford’s global footprint. Support focused on a mix of US university-based programs for research and training; think-tanks for policy-oriented meetings and policy research; and action projects specifically in less developed countries. The Foundation’s focus on peace, freedom, and democracy played out against the Cold War backdrop for scientific and military competition between the United States, the Soviet Union and China.
Under President Hoffman, the Foundation’s work was organized by the areas identified in the Gaither Committee Report: Area One, the Establishment of Peace; Area Two, The Strengthening of Democracy; Area Three, The Strengthening of the Economy; Area Four, Education in a Democratic Society; and Area Five, Individual Behavior and Human Relations.
Program differentiation began in the Gaither era. When he began in 1953, he introduced the following programs, with international work under nearly all of them: International Programs, Public Affairs Programs, Program in Economic Development and Administration (mainly U.S. based), Education Program, The TV-Radio Workshop, and Behavioral Sciences Program. In 1954, the Foundation gave prominence to the international work explicitly through changing the program names and separating international affairs and overseas development. The 1954 program names were: The Advancement of Education, Education for Democracy, Increasing Knowledge of Foreign Areas, Economic Development and Administration, the Behavioral Sciences, and Overseas Development. In 1955, Increasing Knowledge of Foreign Areas became Increasing International Understanding. In 1956, the last year of the Gaither presidency, the program roster read: Education in the United States, The Behavioral Sciences, Public Affairs, Hospital Aid (only in the U.S.), Economic Development and Administration, International Understanding, and Overseas Development. Names changed but the program focus often remained the same.
President Heald maintained the areas of international interest of Hoffman and Gaither. The International Affairs program housed the programs based in the United States, Europe and Japan, with a few activities linking American and developing countries institutions. The Overseas Training and Research Program took over the efforts to increase American understanding of international issues. From 1957-1959, an International Legal Studies program, run from New York, helped build law programs in developing countries. Starting in 1959, the Overseas Development program comprised all the regional and country offices. In fiscal year 1964, Heald convinced the trustees to add a new focus on population, with grants both in the United States and overseas.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 2. Period Summary - The Expansion Era 1950-1965
With the ever-increasing budget and trustee willingness to invade capital, presidents Hoffman, Gaither and Heald oversaw vast growth in the Foundation's international activities in the United States, other developed countries and developing countries. Activities crossed disciplines, institutions, and national boundaries, although few crossed intra-foundation boundaries. Under the three presidents, Foundation staff in various domestic and international offices from New York interacted with the regional and country offices headed by representatives. Usually in this period, however, these offices in fact worked more closely with local governments than with New York staff, reinforcing the commitment to locally led social and economic development in less-developed countries.
The shared values of this early period reflected as much the continuing competition between the Communist and capitalist worlds as the concerns about maintaining peace. The Cold War provided the contextual continuity for grantmaking on the core themes of increasing American understanding of the rest of the world, building and strengthening connections not only with European and Asian democracies but also with Eastern European countries, the Soviet Union, China, and Cuba.
- Travel and Study Awards, 1968-1975; I
  - Ahmad, Bashir, 1968-1974 (Box 1)
  - Fatma, Dr. Matin, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Faridi, Tazeen, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Faruqi, Modh. Akhtar, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Ginai, Naseem Asghar, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Haq, Dr. Israrul, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Hashmi, Zafar Ali, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Ikram, Khalid, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Isani, Usman Ali, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Jamali, Sikandar Hayat, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Jawed, Khalid, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Khan, Khurshid, 1971-1973 (Box 1)
  - Khan, Sarshar Ahmad, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Qureshi, Sarfaraz K., 1972 (Box 1)
  - Razzaque, Mohd. Abdur, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Saifi, M.L., 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Sehrai, Fidaullah, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Wasti, S. Razi, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Afzal, Mohammed, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Ahmad, Mushtaq, 1969-1975 (Box 2)
  - Ahmad, Wajihuddin, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Ahmad, Wajihuddin, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Akhtar, Dr. A. Hafeez, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Azam, Khan Mohammed, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Azfar, J., 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Hassan, Parvez, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Huque, Dr. Heshamul, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Hussain, Ghulam, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Hussain, Syed Munir, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Inayat, M. Rafique, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Khajak, Mohd. Yousuf, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Khan, Abdul Ghaffar, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Khan, Shoaib Sultan, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Khan, Umar Draz, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Kiani, Aquila, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Lord Caradon, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Mudoga, Freda, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Qureshi, Nek Mohd., 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Radhu, Ghulam Mohammed, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Raoof, Mohd. Adbur, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Saeed, Ahmad, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Yagel, Dr. Sadik, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Yusuf, Kaniz Fatima, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Abbasi, Shams, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Ahmad, Meekal, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
  - Ahmad, Naseer, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Ahmad, Nisar, 1970-1975 (Box 3)
  - Ahmad, Nigar R., 1973 (Box 3)
  - Ahsan, Rashida, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Ali, Syed Azad, 1973-1974 (Box 3)
  - Anwar, Rehana, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Ata, Farooq, 1968-1970 (Box 3)
  - Baluch, Mohammad Khan, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Baluch, Shukrulian Khan, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
  - Beg, Razia Azam Ali, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Dani, A.H., 1971 (Box 4)
  - Erkin, Dr. Kandemir, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Feliciano, Dr. Gloria, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Farooq, Arshad, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Hussain, Syed Sajjad, 1973-1974 (Box 4)
- Subject Files, II
  - Grant Projects -- College of Home Economics -- Reports, Mar 1952-Mar 1955 (Box 4)
  - Grant Projects -- College of Home Economics -- Association Conference, Feb 1955-Jan 1957 (Box 4)
  - Grant Projects -- College of Home Economics -- Karachi Council, 1953-1957 (Box 4)
  - Grant Projects -- College of Home Economics -- Karachi -- Architect, 1952-1955 (Box 4)
  - Grant Projects -- College of Home Economics -- Karachi -- General, 1954-1955 (Box 4)
  - Grant Projects -- College of Home Economics -- American Personnel, 1954-1956 (Box 4)
  - Grant Projects -- College of Home Economics -- Karachi General, 1951-1953 (Box 4)
  - Grant Projects -- College of Home Economics -- Tours, Jul-Dec 1954 (Box 4)
  - Grant Projects -- College of Home Economics -- Tucker, 1953-1956 (Box 4)
  - Grant Projects -- Polytechnic Institutes -- Karachi -- General, 1954-1955 (Box 4)
  - Council for the College of Domestic Science -- Architect, 1953 (Box 4)
  - College of Home Economics -- Peshawar, 1952-1956 (Box 4)
  - University of Karachi -- Sound-proofing of the Language Lab, 1968-1967 (Box 4)
  - Pakistan Technical Education Program -- Professional Activities Report, 1963 (Box 5)
  - Pakistan Technical Education Program -- Professional Activities Reports, 1966-1967 (Box 5)
  - Pakistan Technical Education Program -- Professional Activities Reports, 1961-1962 (Box 5)
  - Pakistan Technical Education Program -- Professional Activities Reports, 1965-1966 (Box 5)
  - Pakistan Technical Education Program -- Professional Activities Reports, 1962-1964 (Box 5)
  - Pakistan Technical Education Program -- Professional Activities Reports, 1958-1959 (Box 5)
  - Pakistan Technical Education Project -- Terminal Report, 1961-1963 (Box 5)
  - Technical Education -- General, 1967-1968 (Box 5)
  - Areas of Interest -- Library Assistance (Jerry W. Dye), 1962-1964 (Box 5)
  - Library Assistance (Jerry Dye), 1964 (Box 5)
  - Library Assistance (Jerry Dye), 1965 (Box 5)
  - Grant Projects -- Technical Education Grants -- General, Feb 1954-Feb 1956 (Box 6)
  - Grant Projects -- Survey of Technical Education -- General, Feb-Jul 1954 (Box 6)
  - Technical Education -- General, Apr-Aug 1964 (Box 6)
  - Technical Education -- General, Sep 1964-Oct 1965 (Box 6)
  - Technical Education -- General, Nov 1965-Apr 1967 (Box 6)
  - Technical Education -- General, May-Aug 1967 (Box 6)
  - Polytechnic Institutes --Prospective Teachers Training Program, 1953-1955 (Box 6)
  - Grant Projects -- Polytechnic Institutes -- Karachi -- Architect, 1952-1953 (Box 6)
  - Grant Projects -- Polytechnic Institutes -- Karachi -- Personnel, 1952-1955 (Box 6)
  - Grant Projects -- Polytechnic Institutes -- Dacca -- Personnel, Oct 1953-Mar 1955 (Box 6)
  - Agriculture -- Rice and Sugarcane Crops Seminar, Dec 1974 (Box 6)
  - Agriculture -- International Rice Research Institute, 1969-1972 (Box 6)
  - Agriculture -- A.L.A.D. (Beirut), 1975 (Box 6)
  - Agriculture -- International Association of Agricultural Economists Conference (IAAE), 1972-1974 (Box 6)
  - Agriculture -- General, 1972-1975 (Box 7)
  - Population Matters -- USAID, 1969-1970 (Box 7)
  - Population -- General, 1969-1974 (Box 7)
  - Population -- General, 1975-1977 (Box 7)
  - Population -- Pakistan Population Review, 1972-1973 (Box 7)
  - Population -- International Committee on Population Program Management (ICOMP), 1972-1976 (Box 7)
  - Population -- Ford Foundation/Rockefeller Foundation, 1971-1976 (Box 7)
  - PIDE Project Planning and Evaluation, 1974-1975 (Box 7)
  - Educational Television, 1968-1973 (Box 8)
  - Instructional Technology, 1968-1974 (Box 8)
  - Cultural Interests -- General, 1968-1975 (Box 8)
  - Islam and Social Change -- University of Chicago, 1972-1979 (Box 8)
  - Government of Pakistan -- General Correspondence, 1969-1974 (Box 8)
  - Development Administration and Management -- The Management Association of Pakistan, 1968-1969 (Box 8)
  - Travel and Study Awards -- Finance and Administration, 1978-1980 (Box 8)
  - Reporting -- Pakistan Grants Status -- Grants to Individuals, 1974-1975 (Box 8)
  - West Pakistan Management Association Survey, 1973-1975 (Box 8)
  - Small Industries, 1973-1974 (Box 9)
  - Baluchistan, 1972-1973 (Box 9)
  - Baluchistan Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 9)
  - University of Baluchistan, 1972 (Box 9)
  - Baluchistan -- Forest Department, 1972 (Box 9)
  - Planning Commission, 1969-1970 (Box 9)
  - Pakistan Review, 1969-1970 (Box 9)
  - Agriculture -- Rice, 1972-1974 (Box 9)
  - Language Studies -- Ford Foundation Grants to Pakistan, 1959-1973 (Box 9)
  - Education -- General, 1972-1975 (Box 9)
  - Kinnaird College for Women -- Lahore, 1975-1981 (Box 9)
  - New York General Correspondence, 1973-1979 (Box 10)
  - All Pakistan Women's Association (APWA), 1972-1981 (Box 10)
  - Home Economics -- Early Development of Home Economics in Pakistan 1952-1969, [1970] (Box 10)
  - Women's Act -- General (1/3), 1972-1975 (Box 10)
  - Women's Act -- General (2/3), 1976-1978 (Box 10)
  - Women's Act -- General (3/3), 1979 (Box 10)
  - Women's Act -- General -- Attachment Folder, 1973-1980 (Box 10)
  - Women -- Attachment Folder, 1979-1981 (Box 11)
  - Women's Resource Center, 1976-1979 (Box 11)
  - General Research -- Training File, 1978-1980 (Box 11)
  - Training and Study -- General -- Attachment Folder, 1972-1976 (Box 11)
  - Political Economy of South Asia Project, 1978-1980 (Box 11)
  - Training and Study Program -- General, 1976-1981 (Box 11)
  - University College London, 1973-1979 (Box 11)
  - Harvard Center for International Affairs (Harvard University), 1976-1980 (Box 11)
  - Rural Development -- General, 1977-1981 (Box 11)
  - Rural Development -- Khan, Akhtar Hameed, 1973-1980 (Box 11)
  - Princeton Parvin Fellowships, 1973-1981 (Box 11)
  - Human Rights, 1976-1980 (Box 11)
  - Human Rights -- Attachment Folder, 1980 (Box 11)
  - Islam -- General, 1979-1981 (Box 12)
  - Migration and Refugees -- General, 1978-1981 (Box 12)
  - Migration and Refugees -- General -- Attachment Folder, 1979-1980 (Box 12)
  - Sind Regional Planning Organization (SRPO) -- General, 1979-1981 (Box 12)
  - People's Republic of China, 1978-1981 (Box 12)
  - Social Sciences -- General, 1969-1981 (Box 12)
  - Social Sciences -- Attachments Folder, 1955-1978 (Box 12)
  - Social Science Research in Pakistan -- M. Sinding, 1954-1978 (Box 12)
  - Government of Pakistan -- Reports, 1973-1981 (Box 12)
  - Government of Pakistan -- Policies, 1972-1980 (Box 12)
  - Government of Pakistan -- General, 1975-1980 (Box 12)
  - Provident Fund -- Basic Documents, 1958-1979 (Box 12)
  - Provident Fund -- Minutes of Meetings, 1959-1981 (Box 12)
  - United Nations -- Correspondence, 1975-1981 (Box 13)
  - World Bank (IBRD), 1972-1981 (Box 13)
  - United States Embassy/US AID, 1975-1981 (Box 13)
  - International Manpower Institute, 1972-1977 (Box 13)
  - Ford Foundation -- Program in Pakistan, 1975-1980 (Box 13)
  - International Development Research Centre, 1976-1980 (Box 13)
  - Environment -- Documents, 1972-1981 (Box 13)
  - Center for Agricultural Policy Studies, 1976-1979 (Box 13)
  - University of Karachi -- Population Studies Program, 1974-1981 (Box 13)
  - International Institute of Education (IIE), 1969-1981 (Box 13)
  - Population -- General, 1973-1981 (Box 13)
  - Population -- Organizations -- Family Planning Association, 1974-1981 (Box 13)
  - Population -- Organizations -- Population Council, 1975-1979 (Box 13)
  - Population -- Organizations -- Ford Foundation/Rockefeller Programs, 1976-1981 (Box 13)
  - Agriculture -- Crops -- Maize, 1974-1979 (Box 14)
  - Agriculture -- Crops -- Cotton -- Current, 1965-1981 (Box 14)
  - Agriculture -- Crops -- Rice -- Current, 1974-1980 (Box 14)
  - Agriculture -- Crops -- Wheat -- Current, 1974-1981 (Box 14)
  - Agriculture -- Crops -- Sorghum and Millets, 1975-1977 (Box 14)
  - Agriculture -- Crops -- General, 1975-1980 (Box 14)
  - Agriculture -- Food, 1975-1980 (Box 14)
  - Agriculture -- Fertilizer, 1978-1979 (Box 14)
  - Agriculture -- Nutrition, 1980 (Box 14)
  - Agriculture -- Land Reform, 1977 (Box 14)
  - Agriculture -- General (1/2), 1976-1979 (Box 14)
  - Agriculture -- General (2/2), 1980-1981 (Box 14)
  - Agriculture -- General (Documents), 1979-1981 (Box 14)
  - University of Agriculture -- Faisalabad, 1978-1981 (Box 14)
  - Intermediate Agricultural Mechanical Technology, 1974-1980 (Box 15)
  - Agriculture -- Water Research, 1975-1981 (Box 15)
  - Agriculture -- Organizations -- Rice Research Institute, Kala Shah Kaku, 1975-1981 (Box 15)
  - Agriculture -- Organizations -- ADC NY, 1974-1978 (Box 15)
  - Agriculture -- Organizations -- ALAD, 1975-1976 (Box 15)
  - Agriculture -- Organizations -- International Rice Research Institute (IRRI) -- Current, 1974-1981 (Box 15)
  - Agriculture -- Organizations -- CGIAR, 1974-1980 (Box 15)
  - Agriculture -- Organizations -- ARC (Pakistan), 1975-1980 (Box 15)
  - Agriculture -- Organizations -- CIMMYT, 1975-1981 (Box 15)
  - Boston University, 1976-1981 (Box 15)
  - Berkeley English Language Program in Pakistan, 1980 (Box 15)
  - WAPDA -- Master Planning, 1977-1980 (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous -- General, 1980-1981 (Box 15)
  - Institute of National Languages, 1973-1974 (Box 15)
  - Language and Linguistics in Pakistan, 1970-1977 (Box 15)
  - Hunsberger, I. Moyer, 1968-1976 (Box 15)
  - Rural Unemployment, 1970-1975 (Box 15)
  - Health -- Nutrition -- Population, 1972-1978 (Box 15)
  - Education -- General -- Current, 1975-1981 (Box 16)
  - Education -- General -- Attachment Folder, 1974-1979 (Box 16)
  - Economic Planning -- Economic Review 1975, 9175-1976 (Box 16)
  - New International Economic Order 1977, 1977-1980 (Box 16)
  - International Economics Projects, 1978-1980 (Box 16)
  - Employment, 1971-1979 (Box 16)
  - Cultural Interests -- General, 1976-1981 (Box 16)
  - Cultural Interests -- Consultants, 1970-1980 (Box 16)
  - Cultural Interests -- Reports, 1980; Photos (Box 16)
  - Cultural Interests -- Archaeology -- Museums in Pakistan -- General, 1977-1981 (Box 16)
  - Economics of Pakistan, 1976-1981 (Box 16)
  - Economics in Pakistan -- Masood Akram (Consultant), 1975-1976 (Box 17)
  - Economic Planning and Development -- General, 1974-1981 (Box 17)
  - Economic Planning and Development -- Economic Research Institute, 1975-1981 (Box 17)
  - Ericson, Mr. David M. and Ms. Mia A. M. de Kuijper (Consultants), 1979-1981 (Box 17)
  - Government of Pakistan Regulations (Import Privileges), 1970-1975 (Box 17)
  - Retrenchment, 1975-1978 (Box 17)
  - File House #10, St. 67th Shalimar 7, 1975-1981 (Box 17)
  - Small Causes Court, Karachi -- Miss Talat Hamida Lutfullah v. Ford Foundation in Pakistan -- Suit no. 359 of 1973 (1/4), 1971-1974 (Box 17)
  - Small Causes Court, Karachi -- Miss Talat Hamida Lutfullah v. Ford Foundation in Pakistan -- Suit no. 359 of 1973 (2/4), 1971-1975 (Box 17)
  - Small Causes Court, Karachi -- Miss Talat Hamida Lutfullah v. Ford Foundation in Pakistan -- Suit no. 359 of 1973 (3/4), 1972 (Box 17)
  - Small Causes Court, Karachi -- Miss Talat Hamida Lutfullah v. Ford Foundation in Pakistan -- Suit no. 359 of 1973 (4/4), 1971-1975 (Box 17)
  - Grant Projects -- Polytechnic Institute -- Karachi -- Progress Reports, 1954-1955; Photos (Box 18)
  - Pakistan Technical Education Program -- Professional Activities Report, 1966-1967 (Box 18)
  - Pakistan Technical Education Program -- Professional Activities Reports, 1961-1963 (Box 18)
  - Grant Projects -- Polytechnic Institute -- Karachi -- Reports, 1952-1955; Photos (Box 18)
  - Grant Projects -- Polytechnic Institute -- Correspondence from Wentworth, 1952-1953; Photos (Box 18)
  - Grant Projects -- Polytechnic Institute at Karachi -- Wentworth Institute -- Progress Report, 1953; Photos (Box 18)
  - Grant Projects -- Survey of Technical Education, Feb 1954-May 1960 (Box 19)